<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Reflections upon the new test, and the reply thereto with a letter of Sir Francis Walsingham's, concerning the penal laws made in the reign of Queen Elizabeth.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 39 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58386</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R732</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6019</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13219912</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13219912</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98527</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58386)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98527)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 436:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Reflections upon the new test, and the reply thereto with a letter of Sir Francis Walsingham's, concerning the penal laws made in the reign of Queen Elizabeth.</title>
                  <author>Walsingham, Francis, Sir, 1530?-1590. Letter to Monsieur Critoy.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>"Sir Fr. Walsingham's letter to Monsieur Critoy concerning the Queens proceedings against both papists and Puritans": p. 15-20.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>New test of the Church of England's loyalty.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  Legal status, laws, etc. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Elizabeth, 1558-1603.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98527:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98527:1"/>
            <p>Reflections UPON THE NEW TEST, AND The REPLY Thereto WITH A LETTER OF Sir <hi>FRANCIS WALSINGHAM</hi>'s, Concerning the PENAL LAWS Made in the REIGN of Queen <hi>ELIZABETH.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed in the Year MDCLXXXVII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:98527:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98527:2"/>
            <head>REFLECTIONS UPON THE New Teſt, AND The REPLY thereto.</head>
            <p>THE deſign of the Teſt is to attack the Church of <hi>England</hi>'s Loyalty, and the ſubſtance of it is, That ſhe owns the King Supream Head in Eccleſiaſtical Affairs, that ſhe began under <hi>Ed.</hi> 6. and at his Death indeavour'd to ſet up a Brat of her own, and exclude Queen <hi>Mary</hi> the only Legitimate, becauſe ſhe was a Catholick; after her Death Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> a known Baſtard, rais'd this Church again to ſupport the weakneſs of her Title, and no ſooner was this Church under her re-eſtabliſh'd, than thoſe Cannibal Laws were Enacted of Hanging the Prieſts of the living God, together with other penal Laws; that ſhe Murder'd the Queen of <hi>Scots,</hi> who was the undoubted Heir to the Crown, that to <hi>Charles</hi> I. this Church was faithful, but on the other hand, to force an Univerſal Uniformity to her Liturgy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> was the occaſion of that War, and ſhe now refuſes to repeal the Teſt, and penal Laws; that the King will no longer truſt her, and that ſhe ſhould learn obedience from her Catholick Neighbours. Thus far the Teſt.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:98527:3"/>
            <p>To this is reply'd, That the Church of <hi>England</hi> does own the Kings Supremacy; and therefore thinks her ſelf more Loyal than the Romaniſts, who rob the King of that part of his Prerogative, that after <hi>Ed. 6.</hi> Death, the Kingdom was divided about the Title to the Crown; ſome for Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> ſome for Lady <hi>Jane,</hi> and Proteſtants on both ſides, and while the Title was to them dubious, neither party could be charged with Diſloyalty: That if Queen <hi>Eliz.</hi> was a known Baſtard, the Romaniſts were the diſloyal Party in ſetting her upon the Throne, and excluding the lawful Heir, which they did by a Popiſh Parliament, ſitting at Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s Death, ſo that it appeared by their own Parliament, that <hi>Mary</hi> Queen of <hi>Scots</hi> was not lawful Heir, and therefore it could be no diſloyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in Executing her for Treaſon. That 'twas not the Church of <hi>Englands</hi> Ambition from whence that War in <hi>Charles</hi> I. time enſued, but from the diviſion the Romaniſts had wickedly made amongſt Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, by one call'd <hi>Faithful Commin,</hi> and others of the Fraternity; then the Author recriminates, ſhews it to be the declared opinion of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> that ſhe has power to Depoſe Princes, and gives ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral inſtances where very often they have put that opinion into practice. Thus far the Replyer.</p>
            <p>The Replyer, though he has ſufficiently anſwer'd the Pamphlet; yet ſince Loyalty is almoſt the onely thing, which at this time recommends us to our Princes's Favour; he might, and ought to have given a more ample account of our Fidelity to Princes: I ſhall now therefore take both the <hi>Test</hi> and the <hi>Reply</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to particular Examination, and ſhew the defects of both.</p>
            <p>But, firſt, I would willingly know, what proſpect the Author of the Teſt could have by publiſhing ſuch a Pamphlet? Was it to oblige his Party by drawing
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:98527:3"/> us out to expoſe both their Principles and Practices in point of Civil Obedience? which may be with as great eaſe juſtly done, as we can thrô off that mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and falſe charge of his; or was it to oblige the King by blowing up theſe Fears and Jealouſies, which his Majeſty, a gracious Father of his Country, has us'd means to allay: His Majeſty tells us we are Loyal, and aſſures us of his Protection, the Teſt tells us, we are Snakes in his Boſom, and the King will not protect us: for my part, let this Fellow ſtare and brazen as he pleaſes, I ſhall believe the King, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he would have us think of him.</p>
            <p>When ſo heavy a charge was laid upon our Church, me thinks in reaſon the Author ſhould have ſhew'd the World what Convocation, or at leaſt what pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Doctor of our Communion ever acknowledg'd it as a Principle of our Church, that diſobedience to the ſupream Magiſtrate, was upon any ſcore whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever allowable, that is, that we might refuſe both active and paſſive obedience: for elſe, admit he could inſtance, that ſome of our Communion have acted Diſloyally, it proves no more, than that ſome who have in outward appearance profeſs'd themſelves to be with us, were not really ſo, nor did keep up to the Principles of our Church. What's more common than to ſee a Romaniſt drunk upon a Faſting Day, but unleſs I hear them juſtifie the thing as allowable, ſhall I reaſon from their bare practice, that their Church allows Debauchery upon thoſe dayes ſhe has pointed out for Mortification. Wherefore the Teſts abſolute ſilence herein demonſtrates, either that he is a great Dunce at Argument, or that there is no ſuch thing to be found in our Principles, no, not from the Teſtimony of any ſingle Doctor. And of this defect the Replyer takes no notice.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:98527:4"/>
            <p>The Members of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> ſays the <hi>Test,</hi> were faithful to <hi>Charles I.</hi> but on the other hand their ambition to force Uniformity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> was cauſe of the enſuing War. He means, if to the purpoſe, That an ambition to force an Uniformity in Religion, is Diſloyalty; which is a moſt admirable Diſcovery ! e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially ſince the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> can ſo eaſily clear her ſelf from the guilt of that Ambition. If what he alledgeth were true, his Reprehenſion is juſt like an old Drunkard in a drunken Fit railing againſt Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. But the Replyer has ſhew'd him a more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable and natural cauſe of that War, and has well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd to that Book of Foxes and Fire-brands, which will give a reaſonable Enquirer full ſatisfaction; and further, from thence well obſerves what excellent Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects Romaniſts make to Proteſtant Kings. We are not now to be ſurpriz'd with their <hi>Teſts,</hi> and ſuch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Pamphlets; we are ſenſible the glorious Luſtre of the Church of <hi>England</hi> does ſo offend and dazle their weak Eyes, that it muſt be darken'd, though the Fog be rais'd from Hell; and therefore thus goes on the <hi>Test:</hi> After <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth's death, Proteſtants endeavour'd to ſet up a Brat of their own to exclude Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> becauſe ſhe was a Catholick, at whoſe death Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> raiſed this Church to ſupport the weakneſs of her Title; and then they Murther'd the Queen of <hi>Scots,</hi> who was the undoubted Heir to the Crown.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Brat, to exclude Queen </hi> Mary, <hi>becauſe a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick:</hi> Nay, we were more wicked than this: for we ſet this Brat up too, to exclude Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe was a Proteſtant: for in excluding one, we excluded both, And if we thought we had power to pull down, and put up, as the Popes aſſume, why did we not as well put up <hi>Elizabeth</hi> as Lady <hi>Jane?</hi> The <hi>Index Expurgatorius</hi> has not yet done the honour of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:98527:4"/> a Viſit to our Modern Hiſtories, and therefore in them we find, that by a Cabal onely of ſome of King <hi>Edward'</hi> s Council, he was prevail'd upon by his laſt Will, and Letters-Patents, to ſettle the Crown up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Lady <hi>Jane.</hi> This by the Procurers of the Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement, was declared to the People, and ſhe was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed Queen. Queen <hi>Mary</hi> alſo ſhe puts up her Title. Upon this the Kingdom was in a general di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraction; but the greateſt part of Proteſtants were with Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> and 'twas through their means ſhe ever reach'd the Throne. But I ſhall forbear men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioning how nobly ſhe rewarded their Services; 'tis enough to my purpoſe, to prove they were Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, and that they were ſo, is clear, becauſe the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Party were ſo conſiderable in the Kingdom at that time, that they might have carried whatſoever Intereſt they had eſpouſed: But it appears further by the Queens promiſe at that time to her Army, which was, That ſhe would never alter the Religion eſtabliſh'd by <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth; and 'twas very likely ſhe ſhould think to engage a Popiſh Army by a Promiſe never to alter the Proteſtant Religion. This then is the truth of the Caſe: The Lady <hi>Jane</hi> was put up by a ſmall deſigning Party, who had got ſeveral ignorant people to believe that the deceaſed King had made her a good Title; but the body of Proteſtants were faithful to Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> and forc'd her way to the Crown. To whom ſucceeded Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> whom this modeſt Gentleman honours with the Title of <hi>Known Baſtard.</hi> If it be ſo, yet theſe things fall out a little unhappily: for the Proteſtants ſet up the Legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate Queen <hi>Mary;</hi> and as the Replyer truly obſerves, <hi>The Members of a Popiſh Parliament, ſetting at Queen </hi> Mary' <hi>s death, were the firſt that mov'd in proclaiming the Known Baſtard Queen</hi> Eliz. Thus 'tis taking it for
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98527:5"/> granted what he affirms; but now for truth: By re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular proceedings in this Kingdom, <hi>Katherine</hi> Mother of Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> and <hi>Hen. 8.</hi> were divorc'd <hi>à vinculo Matrimonii,</hi> then he takes to Wiſe <hi>Ann B.</hi> of whom is born Q. <hi>Eliz.</hi> This Divorce was juſt, or not; if juſt, there's no queſtion of Q. <hi>Eliz.</hi> Legitimation; if not juſt, it muſt be either becauſe there is no Power in this Kingdom to determine in ſuch caſes, or that in this they had not juſtly determin'd. If theſe caſes are not determinable here, they muſt be determined by a For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Juriſdiction, or no-where; and to Appeal to a Forreign Juriſdiction, in any caſe, is a <hi>Praemunire,</hi> by a Statute made in Popiſh times. That they made a juſt Determination, they have the warrant of moſt of the Univerſities beyond Sea, for whoſe Opinions <hi>H.</hi> 8. ſent; and the perpetual ſtanding Law of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which in this caſe was always judg'd to be grounded upon the Law of God: for which, ſee <hi>Harri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> and Dr. <hi>Burnwell</hi>'s uſe in Lord <hi>Vaughan</hi>'s Reports. Now let the Reader judge: But why ſhould we be forc'd to diſpute this matter, when by Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>triceſſ. quin. H. 8.</hi> 'tis ſetled that both <hi>Mary</hi> and <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizabeth</hi> ſhall inherit? What more then had we to do, but to pay our Obedience to our Law-makers? which I hope will ſomething excuſe us, if 'twere true, as 'tis not, that <hi>Mary</hi> Queen of <hi>Scots,</hi> before that Act, had right to be Succeſſour to our Queen <hi>Mary:</hi> But the <hi>Test</hi> will have the Queen of <hi>Scots</hi> Title preferable; yet has not ſomuch as indeavoured to give us a reaſon for that opinion: To this his Magiſterial Affirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on we oppoſe; firſt, The Arguments already offered for Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Legitimation: Secondly, The Act of Parliament, juſt before mentioned: Thirdly, As the Replyer has urg'd, the unanimous Opinion of a Popiſh Parliament, ſitting at Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s Death;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98527:5"/> and indeed he might have ſaid, the unanimous conſent of the whole Nation? For I defie this <hi>Test Writer</hi> to produce, one that publickly diſſented to proclaim Queen <hi>Elizabeth:</hi> So univerſally then was her Title allow'd, and her Perſon eſteemed. I have yet this fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reaſon, That at Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s Death, the Queen of <hi>Scots</hi> did not ſo much as put in any Claim to the Crown; but on the contrary, in the firſt of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Reign, there was a very indearing, and Siſterly Correſpondence between the two Queens, every Week Letters of Kindneſs, and Civility paſſed, which was very unlike the carriage of Competitours for a Crown; of the truth of this, any one will be ſatisfied, that ſo much as looks into the Memoires of Sir <hi>James Melvill,</hi> the Queen of <hi>Scots</hi> great Miniſter.</p>
            <p>But if after all this, you will have it that this Queen did pretend to the Crown; then you have given a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good reaſon for her Execution; if ſhe did not, then certainly 'twas poſſible for her to be guilty of Crimes deſerving Death: Wherefore, if we are chargable for that Action, 'tis our Juſtice, not our Loyalty, muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the blemiſh: But to excuſe our ſelves herein, let it be conſidered. That when the Queen of <hi>Scots</hi> was forc'd by her own Subjects, to fly to <hi>England</hi> for Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, ſhe was received by Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and her Council, with intention to reſtore her to her Crown, and Country, as is evident by two Papers; one is the Advice Sir <hi>Henry Mildmay</hi> gave about it; the other, a Letter of the Earl of <hi>Leiceſter</hi>'s to the Earl of <hi>Suſſex;</hi> both which may be ſeen copy'd immediately from the Originals in Dr. <hi>Burnet's</hi> Hiſt. <hi>Reformation.</hi> And it can't be ſuppos'd, that 'twas for nothing that our Queen's intentions received this turn: The Queen of <hi>Scots</hi> of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficious Friends had a great mind to ſee an end of <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth</hi>'s Reign, nor did they leave any thing unat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98527:6"/> to effect it, either by ſecret Attempts, or publick Rebellions; the Queen ſuſpected from whence all this came, and at laſt was ſatisfied, when ſhe ſound the Queen of <hi>Scots</hi> own hand to a Letter wrote to <hi>Babington</hi> and <hi>Ballard</hi> about their Plot; and then our Queen thought 'twas high time, both for the ſafety of her ſelf, &amp; the Kingdom, to bring the Queen of <hi>Scots</hi> to her Tryal, upon which ſhe was found guilty of Treaſon.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now ſum up this matter. Under <hi>Edward</hi> you ſay we firſt began, during whoſe Reign you have nothing to ſay, as to the point of Loyalty, againſt us: and I have fully prov'd we brought Queen <hi>Mary</hi> his Succeſſor to the Throne. To her Succeſſour Queen <hi>Eliz.</hi> you your ſelf own we were a Prop, and we did indeed help to defeat the diſloyal attempts of Romaniſts againſt her. I have proved that <hi>Mary</hi> Queen of <hi>Scots</hi> was not deprived of any preſent Right, and of a future Right ſhe might be deprived, without any Act of Diſloyalty. Under King <hi>James, Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi>'s Succeſſour, the <hi>Test</hi> does not ſo much as affirm we were diſloyal: To King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, King <hi>James</hi>'s Succeſſour, our Author acknowledges we were faithful in all his Troubles: Nor does he in the leaſt blame us in <hi>Charles</hi> the Second's time. Thus, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the leaſt appearance of Diſloyalty, have we brought our ſelves to this preſent King, who has ſeen our forwardneſs to be as Loyal to him as to his Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours: 'Tis well known what ſort of a Lower Houſe that was which brought in the Bill of Excluſion; but when it came to the Lords Houſe, (from whence the Popiſh Lords were excluded) they ſhew'd their Fidelity by throwing it out. How readily, at <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth</hi>'s appearance did the Parliament proteſt to ſtand by the King, and how freely did divers Proteſtant Gentlemen venture themſelves in the Kings Cauſe, and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98527:6"/> this they muſt always upon occaſion do, if they mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure their actions either by the Principles, or Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of our Church.</p>
            <p>Our Author therefore is a great Friend to the King, in calling us to learn of our Catholick Neighbours, which is to debauch this good Principle; and I ſhall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to the World ſome of the Leſſons they would teach us: at our entrance we muſt learn that Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction (which is a glorious part of the Kings Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative) belongs to the Pope; ſo ſtrongly does the <hi>Teſt</hi> fancy, that their Church of right aſſumes this Power; that he ridicules the contrary Opinion, as a particular Revelation to the Church of <hi>England.</hi> In anſwer to this, the Replyer has well referr'd to Dr. <hi>Barrow,</hi> and Lord <hi>Cook,</hi> but becauſe ſome may not have theſe Books, I ſhall give one or two plain inſtances: <hi>Greg. 1. 15.</hi> Ep. 11. 56. doth alledge divers Laws of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Emperours, concerning Eccleſiaſtical affairs, as obligatory Rules of practice; and divers Laws con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning things Eccleſiaſtical, made by the Emperour, are extant in the Codes of <hi>Theodoſius</hi> and <hi>Juſtinian.</hi> The Chriſtian Emperours took upon them to depoſe Biſhops and Popes, (thô ſince the Popes are even with them) <hi>Conſtantius</hi> baniſh'd Pope <hi>Liberius,</hi> and put another in his room: <hi>Otho</hi> put out <hi>John</hi> the Twelfth, <hi>Juſtinian</hi> depoſed Pope <hi>Silverius,</hi> and baniſh'd Pope <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilius;</hi> and the ſame Emperour preſcrib'd Conditions and Qualifications concerning the Ordination of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops; and ſubjoyns, <hi>Si quis autem citra memora tam obſervationem Epiſcopus ordinetur, jubemus hunc omnibus modis Epiſcopatu depelli. Juſtin. Novel. 123. Ca. 1. But if any Biſhop be Ordain'd without uſing our foremention'd conſtitution, we Command, that by all means he be remov'd from his Biſhoprick. Omnes,</hi> ſayes <hi>Leo 1.</hi> to <hi>Theodocius</hi> the Emperour.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:98527:7"/> 
               <hi>Partiam Eccleſiae noſtrarum, omnes manſuetudini veſtrae cum gemitibus &amp; Lacrymis ſupplicant Sacerdotes, ut ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neralem Synodum jubeatis intra Italiam celebrari: Leo 1. Ep.</hi> 42. nor was this power uſurp'd by the Emperours, as ſometimes loyal Catholicks pretend. No, quite contrary, <hi>Semper fuit Orthodoxis, &amp; piis Imperatori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, &amp;c.</hi> This is what the Pious and Orthodox Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours did. <hi>Juſtin in Syn. 5. Collat. 1. p.</hi> 209. but what's yet higher, <hi>Haec</hi> (ſays the Councel of <hi>Arles) Domino Imperatori praeſentanda decrevimus, poſcentes ejus Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentiam ut ſi quid hîc minus est, ejus prudentiâ Supplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, ſi quid ſecus quàm ſe ratio habet, ejus judicio emende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur; ſi quid rationabiliter taxatum est, ejus adjutario divinâ opitulante Clementiâ perficiatur.</hi> Councel. Arel. 4. ca. 26. Ann. 813. <hi>Sub Carolo M. Theſe things we have Decreed to be preſented to our Lord the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, deſiring his Clemency, that if any thing be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective, it may be ſupplied by his Prudence; if any thing be unreaſonable, it may be corrected by his Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; if any thing be reaſonably ordered, it may, by his help, the Divine Grace aſſiſting, be Perfected.</hi> So that it ſeems notwithſtanding the bluſtering the Popes make now, it was a revelation to all the Churches of the World in the firſt Ages, that the Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction was in the Temporal Magiſtrate. This alſo have Papiſt Kings and their Lay-Subjects juſtified in <hi>England. Xenulphus</hi> by his Letters Pattents, did grant to Abbot <hi>Ruchin, Quod praedictus Ruchinus, &amp;c. That the ſaid</hi> Ruchin <hi>ſhould for ever be free from all Epiſcopal Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction whatſoever.</hi> This was pretty well for a Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Prince without Eccleſiaſtical Power; and to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate that he was not ſingular in aſſuming this Power, this Charter was confirmed by King <hi>Edwin,</hi> and pleaded the 1 <hi>H.</hi> 7. and allowed and continued till the diſſolution of that Abby in <hi>H.</hi> 8. When <hi>H.</hi> 1. found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98527:7"/> the Abby of <hi>Reading,</hi> the Charter run thus: <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricus Dei, &amp;c. Statuimus tam Eccleſiaſticae quam Regiae proſpectu poteſtatis, ut, &amp;c.</hi> We appoint as well by our Eccleſiaſtical as Temporal Power, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In the 25 <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. by a Parliament held at <hi>Carliſle,</hi> it is declared, That the Holy Church of <hi>England</hi> was founded in the State of Prelacy by the King, and his Progenitors, the Popes Uſurpations complained on; and enacted they ſhould not be ſuffered. By a Statute made 16 <hi>R. 2. ca.</hi> 5. It is declared, That the Crown of <hi>England</hi> is Subject to none but God. Of this opinion was <hi>Bracton,</hi> who wrote in <hi>H.</hi> 3d's time, <hi>Omnis,</hi> ſays he, <hi>quidem ſub Rege &amp; ipſe ſub nullo, ſed tantum ſab Deo. Lib. 1. ca 8. nu. 5. Every one owes Obedience to the King, but he to none but GOD.</hi> I muſt give one inſtance more, if it be only to ſhew the nature of a Begotted Papiſt. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. much concern'd, that his Subjects would deprive him of his right by Appeals to <hi>Rome,</hi> by a Statute it was made a <hi>Praemunire,</hi> the hearty Begots did ſo rail and curſe at the Executors of that Law, that the Kingdom was obliged to make a Statute on purpoſe to prevent ſuch defamations. But when after many ſtruglings the Popes did begin to finger this Juriſdiction, as if poyſon'd with their touch, it immediately ſwells to ſuch a prodigious magnitude, as quite to over ſhadow, and cruſh all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Powers; now 'tis <hi>Hunc unum, &amp;c.</hi> Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the Fifth, in his Bull that Excommunicates Queen <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth, Him alone</hi> (ſays he, meaning himſelf) <hi>he made Prince over all People, and all Kingdoms, to pluck up, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy, ſcatter, conſume, plant and build,</hi> &amp;c. So that Temporal Princes are but as ſo many Pagents to be ſet up, and pull'd down as the Infallible Head ſhall ſee cauſe; and an Emperour is no more to a Pope now, than a Pope was to an Emperour heretofore: To prove this, the Replyer has given ſeveral very true ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98527:8"/> to which I ſhall add, That in King <hi>John</hi>'s time, the Loyal Popiſh Barons were in open Rebellion; The Pope inſtead of uſing his pretended Authority to reduce them to their Allegiance, he takes advantage of the King's neceſſities, and will by no means permit him to nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate a Succeſſour to the deceaſed Archbiſhop of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury;</hi> but for ſo doing the King was Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated; this, with the King of <hi>France</hi> his appearing in the Pope's defence, incourag'd the Barons to continue in their Rebellion, and to calumniate their King with the moſt approbrious language, as Infidel, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that no King ever indured the like; finding himſelf on all hands thus oppreſs'd, his ſubmiſſion to the Pope was abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely neceſſary, and therefore now tenders him his Crown, which the Pope by his Legate received; upon this (and all but reaſon) the King is Abſolved, but ſtill the hardy Barons refuſe their duty, till the King had ratified their Priviledges, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which he was forc'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Oath to agree to. But the King being now a good Child of the Church, is diſcharged by the Pope from theſe condeſcentions to the Barons, the whole compact is declared Null, the King's Oath Diſpenc'd with, and the Barons Excommunicated till they ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the Sentence. This is ſomething like, to whip and ſtroke them by turns! Thus the Heaven Door is open'd and ſhut in a breath, that no man alive can be ſure whether he ſhall go in or out.</p>
            <p>When Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> came to this Crown, Sir <hi>Edward Karn</hi> was by her direction to inform the Pope thereof, who made this humble and obliging return, <hi>That</hi> England <hi>was held in fee of the Apoſtolick See, that ſhe could not ſucceed, being illegitimate; nor could be contradict the Declarations made in that matter by his Predeceſſors,</hi> Clement <hi>the Seventh and</hi> Paul <hi>the Third: He ſaid it was great boldneſs in her to aſſume to the Crown without his conſent</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:98527:8"/> 
               <hi>or which in Reaſon ſhe deſerv'd no favour at his hands; yet if ſhe would renounce her Pretenſions, and refer her ſelf wholly to him, he would ſhew a fatherly affection to her, and do every thing for her that could conſiſt with the Dignity of Apoſtolick See;</hi> ſo far the <hi>Servus Servorum.</hi> In this haughty ſpeech 'tis not ſo much the Queens illegitimation is complain'd on, as her great boldneſs to aſſume the Crown without conſent of his Holineſs: for if ſhe will at laſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, here's great hopes for her, notwithſtanding her Ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitimation. But his Succeſſor <hi>Pius</hi> IV. leaves her in no man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of doubt. He ſent one <hi>Parpalia</hi> to her to promiſe, that if ſhe would join her ſelf to the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> he would diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>annul the Sentence againſt her Mother's Marriage, &amp;c. Hence I obſerve, that the Popes what e're they ſaid, did not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve Q. <hi>Eliz.</hi> Illegitimate, or elſe what's worſe, they declare that for their Temporal Intereſt they would make that lawful which the Law of God had made unlawful for if Q. <hi>Eliz.</hi> was a Baſtard, ſhe was ſo, becauſe <hi>Hen.</hi> the 8's. Marriage with his firſt Wife was lawful, who was living when <hi>Eliz.</hi> was born of another woman; if ſo, nothing is plainer than that this ſecond Marriage was againſt the Law of God. But 'tis all nothing, there had been no harm done, no rightful heir diſſeiz'd, no title of a Baſtard ſet up, had <hi>Eliz.</hi> made her acknowledgments that <hi>England</hi> was held in fee of the Apoſtolick See. So ſpeaks the Shepherd, and the ſheep know his voice.</p>
            <p>In fine, the King depoſing Doctrine is not only practiſed by one or two wicked Infallible Heads; but 'tis the ſetled Doctrine of their Church; 'tis that their <hi>Lateran</hi> Council, and a long Succeſſion of Popes have declared, and that which their beſt men have imploy'd their Pens to maintain; for which ſee the Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln's Brutum Fulmen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whether the Teſt or Penal Laws ought to be aboliſhed is a ſubject more proper for the King and Parliament than
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98527:9"/> us: But when you call us Cannibals for making them, you ſpeak like a man of ſenſe, and ought to be conſidered, tho the Replier has taken but little notice of it: their words are theſe <q>And they (meaning the Church of <hi>England)</hi> no ſooner found themſelves re-eſtabliſht, then they Enacted thoſe bloody <hi>Cannibal</hi> Laws to hang, draw and quarter the Prieſts of the living God: Impriſonment, Baniſhments, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſcation of Goods were the moderate Church of <hi>England</hi>'s Laws, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> No ſooner, he ſays, were they reeſtabliſht, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> Now one would think by this repreſentation, that this Law he ſo abhors, was made the next hour after the Queen was proclaim'd, and yet in truth, 'twas the 27 year of the Queens Reign before this Law had birth. Well, but if <hi>Cannibals</hi> they muſt be, who Enact Sanguinary Laws a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe that purely diſſent in matters of Religion, I know no Church deſerves the honour of that title but yours: your lenity towards Hereticks (and all are Hereticks with you, that are not of your faith) is ſo univerſally known, that 'tis in vain to trouble the world with particular inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: however if you pleaſe, you may look in Qu. <hi>Mary</hi>'s days, look into the Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln</hi>'s Book, and when you are looking, look into <hi>France:</hi> But why do I cry look here, or look there, when 'tis impoſſible to look amiſs? However, ſince to recriminate is no juſtification, and ſince we hear that you pride your ſelves to talk of our Penal Laws, endeavouring to render us extreamly cruel, I ſhould apply my ſelf particularly to ſhew the reaſons and ſteps of thoſe Laws, did I not find it incomparably well done to my hands by a Letter, which 'tis great pity the whole Kingdom has not read; and tho it be long, yet there being not a ſentence in it not full of weight, I will for the publick good tranſcribe the whole, which fully vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicates us in this point.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:98527:9"/>
            <head>Sir <hi>Fr. Walſingham</hi>'s Letter to Monſieur <hi>Critoy,</hi> concerning the Queens proceedings againſt both <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Puritans.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHereas you deſire to be advertiz'd, touching the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings here in Eccleſiaſtical Cauſes, becauſe you ſeem to note in them ſome Inconſtancy and Variation, as if we inclin'd ſometimes to one ſide, and ſometimes to another; and as if that Clemency and Lenity were not us'd of late, that was us'd in the beginning: All which you imputed to your own ſuperficial <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding of the Affairs of this State, having, notwithſtanding Her Majeſty's doing in ſingular Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence, as the real Pledges which She hath given unto the World of her Sincerity in Religion, and of the Wiſdom in Government, well meriteth.</p>
            <p>I am glad of this occaſion, to import that little I know in that Matter unto you, both for your own Satisfaction, and to the end you may make uſe thereof, towards any that ſhall not be ſo modeſtly and reaſonably minded, as you are.</p>
            <p>I find Her Majeſties Proceedings to have been grounded upon two Principles.</p>
            <p>The one, that Conſciences are not to be forced, but to be won and reduced by force of Truth, with aid of time, and uſe of good means of Inſtructions and Perſwaſion.</p>
            <p>The other, That Cauſes of Conſciences, when they exceed their bounds, and grow to be matter of Faction, loſe their Nature, and that Sovereign Princes ought diſtinctly to puniſh their Practices and Contempt, tho coloured with the Pretences of Conſcience and Religion.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:98527:10"/>
            <p>According to theſe Principles, Her Majeſty coming to the Crown, utterly diſliking the Tyranny of <hi>Rome,</hi> which had uſed by Terror and Rigour to ſettle Commandments of mens Faith and Conſciences; Tho as a Princeſs of great Wiſdom and Magnanimity, She ſuffered but the Exerciſe of one Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; yet her Proceedings towards the Papist, was with great Lenity, expecting the good Effects which time might work in them; and therefore Her Majesty revived not the Laws made in the 28th and 35th of her Fathers Reign, whereby the Oath of Supremacy might have been offered at the Kings pleaſure to any Subject, ſo he kept his Conſcience, ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er ſo modestly to himſelf, and the refuſal to take the ſame Oath, without further Circumstances, was made Treaſon. But con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe, Her Majesty not liking to make Windows into Mens hearts and ſecret thoughts, except the abundance of them did over flow into overt and expreſs Acts or Affirmations, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered Her Law ſo as it restraineth every manifest Diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience in impugning and impeaching; adviſedly and malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, Her Majesties Supream Power, maintaining and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolling a Forreign Juriſdiction: And as for the Oath, it was altered by Her Majesty, into a more grateful Form: the hardneſs of the name and Appeſtation of Supream Head, was removed, and the Penalty of the refuſal thereof, turned only to diſablement to take any Promotion, or to exerciſe any charge, and yet of Liberty to be reinvested therein, if any man ſhould accept thereof, during his Life. But after, when <hi>Pius Quintus</hi> Excommunicated Her Majesty, and the Bulls of Excommunication were publiſhed in <hi>London,</hi> whereby Her Majesty was in a ſort preſcribed, and that thereupon as upon a principal motive or preparative, followed the Rebellion in the <hi>North,</hi> yet becauſe the ill humours of the Realm were by that Rebellion partly purged, and that ſhe feared at that time no forreign Invaſion, and much leſs the attempt of any within the Realm, not back'd by ſome potent power and ſuccour from
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98527:10"/> without, ſhe contented her ſelf to make a Law againſt that ſpecial Caſe of bringing in, and publiſhing any Bulls, or the like Inſtruments; whereunto was added a Prohibition, upon pain, not of Treaſon, but of an inferiour degree of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, againſt the bringing of the <hi>Agnus Dei's,</hi> and ſuch other Merchandiſe of <hi>Rome,</hi> as are all known, not to be any eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial part of the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> Religion, but only to be uſed in practice, as Love tokens, to inchant and bewitch the peoples affections, from their Allegiance to their natural Soveraign. In all other points her Majeſty continued her former Lenity: But when about the Twentieth year of her Reign, ſhe had diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd in the King of <hi>Spain</hi> an intention to invade her Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions; and that a principal part of the Plot, was to prepare a Party within the Realm, that might adhere to the Forreign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; and that the Seminaries began to bloſſom, and to ſend forth dayly Prieſts, and Profeſſed men, who ſhould by Vow taken at <hi>Shrift,</hi> reconcile her Subjects from their Obedience, yea, and hind many of them to attempt againſt her Majeſties Sacred Perſon; and that, by the Poiſon which they ſpread, the humours of moſt Papiſts were altered, and that they were no more Papiſt in Conſcience, and of Softneſs, but Papiſt in Pactiou: Then were there new Laws made, for the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſuch as ſhould ſubmit themſelves to ſuch reconcile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or renunciation of Obedience. And becauſe it was a Treaſon carried in the Clouds, and in wonderful ſecrecy, and come ſeldom to light, and that there was no preſuſpicion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſo great, as the Recuſancy to come to Divine Service, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was ſet down by their Decrees, that to come to Church before Reconciliation, was to live in Schiſm; but to come to Church after reconcilement, was abſolutely heretical and damnable. Therefore there were added Laws containing puniſhment Pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niary, <hi>viz.</hi> ſuch as might not enforce Conſciences, but to infeeble and impoveriſh the means of thoſe about whom it reſteth indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent and ambiguous, whether they were reconciled or not:
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98527:11"/> And when, notwithſtanding all this proviſion, the Poiſon was diſperſed ſo ſecretly, as that there was no means to ſtay it, I ut by reſtraining the Merchants that brought it in: Then Laſtly, there was added a Law, whereby ſuch ſeditious Prieſts, of new Erection, were exiled; and thoſe that were at that time within the Land, ſhipped over, and ſo commanded to keep hence upon pain of Treaſon. This hath been the proceeding, tho intermingled, not only with ſundry Examples of her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Grace towards ſuch as in her wiſdom ſhe knew to be Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt in Conſcience, and not Faction and Singularity, but alſo with extraordinary mitigation towards the offenders in the higheſt Degree, committed by Law, if they would but proteſt, that if in Caſe this Realm ſhould be invaded with a Forreign Army, by the Popes's authority, for the Catholick Cauſe, as they term it, they would take part with her Majeſty, and not adhere to her Enemies.</p>
            <p>For the other Party, which have been offenſive to the State, though in another Degree, which named themſelves Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, and we commonly call <hi>Puritans,</hi> this hath been the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding towards them. A great while, when they inveighed againſt ſuch abuſes in the Church, as Pluralities, Non-reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and the like; their Zeal was not Condemned, only their Violence was ſometimes Cenſured. When they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed the uſe of ſome Ceremonies and Rites, as Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions, they were tollerated with much Connivency and Gentleneſs; yea, when thy called in Queſtion the Superiority of Biſhops, and pretended to a Democracy in the Church; yet, their Propoſitious were here conſidered, and by contrary Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings debated and diſcuſſed; yet all this while, it was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived that their Courſe was dangerous, and very popular: As, becauſe <hi>Papiſtry</hi> was odious, therefore it was ever in their Mouths, that they ſought to Purge the Church from the Reliques of <hi>Papiſtry;</hi> a thing acceptable to the People, who love ever to run from one extream to another.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:98527:11"/>
            <p>Becauſe multitudes of Rogues, and Poverty, was an Eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſore, and a diſlike to every man; therefore they put into the Peoples head, that if Diſcipline were planted, there ſhould be no Vagabonds nor Beggars, a thing very plauſible: And in like manner they promiſed the People, many of the impoſſible wonders of their Diſcipline; beſides, they opened to the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple a way to Government, by their Conſiſtory and <hi>Presbytery;</hi> a thing, though in conſequence no leſs prejudicial to the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of private men, than to the Soveraignty of Princes, yet in firſt ſhew very Popular. Nevertheleſs this, except it were ſome few that entred into extream contempt, was born with, becauſe they pretended in Dutiful manner to make Propoſitions; and to leave it to the Providence of God, and the Authority of the Magiſtrate. But now of late years, when there iſſued from them that affirmed, the conſent of the Magiſtrate was not to be attended; when under pretence of a Confeſſion, to avoid Slander and Imputations, they combined themſelves by Claſſes and Subſcriptions, when they deſcended into that vile and baſe means of defacing the Government of the Church by ridiculous Paſquils; when they began to make many Subjects in doubt to take Oaths, which is one of the Fundamental parts of Juſtice in this Land; and in all places, when they began both to vaunt of their ſtrength, and number of their Partizans and Followers, and to uſe Comminations that their Cauſe would prevail, tho uproar and Violence; then it appeared to be no more: Zeal, no more Conſcience, but meer Faction and Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: and therefore, though the State were compelled to hold ſomewhat a harder hand to reſtrain them than before, yet was it with as great moderation, as the Peace of the State or Church could permit. And therefore, Sir, to conclude, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der uprightly of theſe matters, and you ſhall ſee Her Majeſty is no more a Temporizer in Religion: It is not the ſucceſs A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, nor the Change of Servants here at home, can alter her; only as the things themſelves alter, She applyed her Religious
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:98527:12"/> Wiſdom to Methods correſpondent unto them; ſtill retaining the Two Rules before mentioned, in dealing tenderly with Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, and yet in diſcovering Faction from Conſcience, and Softneſs from Singularity. <hi>Farewell.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your loving Friend, F. Walſingham.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:98527:12"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
